Guide to the Janice Gorn Papers MC 98
New York University Archives
Janice Gorn Papers
1940-1988
MC 98
New York University Archives
1.5 linear feet (three boxes)
The Janice Gorn Papers cover the professional life of Janice Gorn, a professor of education at New York University from the 1960s-1990s. The papers contain correspondence, syllabi, dissertation materials, and audio tapes of lectures given at NYU during the 1970s.
Gorn, Janice L.
Biography of Janice Gorn
Janice Gorn was a professor of Interdisciplinary Studies and Education and an administrator at New York University from the 1960s through the 1990s. Gorn received her Ph.D. from NYU in 1958 and worked as a professor at Paterson State College from 1959-1961. In 1961 she was hired as an Assistant Professor of Education. By 1969 she had been appointed to the School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Arts Professions (SEHNAP) as a Professor of Interdisciplinary Studies and the only professor appointed solely to the Interdisciplinary Studies program. In 1978, Gorn won a Great Teacher Award, and she continued to work as a professor until the 1990s, most often teaching courses on contemporary issues in education.
Additionally, she remained active in the dissertation proposal seminar and served on all of the doctoral dissertation committees. The main focus of her own publishing was on improving students' writing ability, and she frequently argued for a required course for teaching and learning of spoken English alongside previously required writing classes.
She was also active in University administration and served on a number of University committees and as an Ombudsman.
Source: Biographical file for Janice Gorn, New York University Archives
Separated Material
Photographs previously included in the collection were moved to the University Archives Photograph Collection and organized by the subject of each photograph. Please contact the University Archives for a list of photographs originally part of the collection.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Janice Gorn to the University Archives from 1984-1993.
Scope and Content
The Janice Gorn Papers document her experiences as a professor at New York University. The papers are almost entirely professional in nature and focus on her academic life.
Correspondence makes up a large portion of the collection. Gorn wrote extensively to other academics, and her papers contain her correspondence with Walter MacKeller, Adolphe E. Meyer, George Nelson and Geoffrey Bruun. The teaching materials contain syllabi from the classes Gorn taught from 1968-1981 as well as a draft of Gorn's book Style guide for the writing of scholarly papers, masters' theses and doctoral dissertations, published in 1971. The dissertation materials are made up of letters Gorn wrote to various publishers and repositories asking for permission to use quotations from their materials in her dissertation.
The final series is a collection of audio tapes that Gorn collected of speakers and performers. The tapes cover lectures from 1969-1981, and have topics as varied as in-vitro fertilization and Freud. All of the tapes are labeled with speaker and date and some also indicate titles of the presentations. An inventory annotated by Gorn is included with the tapes, where she described each speaker and detailed their accomplishments and important publications.
Arrangement
The materials in the first two series are arranged by correspondent or type of material and then chronologically. The third series adheres to Gorn's original arrangement. The collection is arranged in three series:
Arrangement
Correspondence
Teaching Materials
Audio Tapes
Access Restrictions
The cassette tapes in the collection have not been digitized. Please contact the New York University Archives for access. Box 1, Folder 1 contains personal information that has been restricted.
Bruun, Geoffrey, 1898-1988; MacKeller, Walter; Meyer, Adolphe E.; Nelson, George, 1908-1986; Correspondence.; Dissertations.; Education |x Study and Teaching |z United States.; New York University |x Faculty |x Women.; New York University |x Faculty |y 20th century.; New York University. School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Arts Profession.; New York University. School of Education.; Syllabi.
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Adolphe E. Mayer, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Adolphe E. Meyer, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - George Nelson, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Geoffrey Bruun, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II. Teaching and Dissertation Materials
  - Course Syllabi, Reports, 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Course Syllabi, 1968-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writing Style Guide, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dissertation Materials, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation Materials, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dissertation Materials (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dissertation Materials, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III. Audio Tapes
  - William J. Sweeney III, M.D., "In Vitro Fertilization-Scientific Ethical and Human Considerations", 1979 February 14 (Box 3, Cassette 1)
  - William J. Sweeney III, M.D., "The Ethics of Medical Research", 1978 February 15 (Box 3, Cassette 2)
  - George Nelson, "Seeing", 1977 May 11 (Box 3, Cassette 3)
  - Robert B. McKay, "Resolution of Civil and Criminal Disputes", 1977 November 30 (Box 3, Cassette 4)
  - Curtis Williams, "Science and Human Values", 1979 April 25 (Box 3, Cassette 5)
  - John P. Spiegel, M.D., 1970 December 16 (Box 3, Cassette 6)
  - Anthony Storr, M.D., "Freud and Art", 1976 April 28 (Box 3, Cassette 7)
  - William J. Sweeney III, M.D., "Problem-Solving with Microsurgery in Gynecological Patients", 1980 February 13 (Box 3, Cassette 8)
  - Robert B. McKay, "The Impact of Law on Education E10.2001", 1980 October 15 (Box 3, Cassette 9)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Deviant Behavior: Beyond Freud & Durkheim I", 1979 November 28 (Box 3, Cassette 10)
  - Richard Cloward, "The Urban Crisis & Fiscal & Political Change", 1971 October 6 (Box 3, Cassette 11)
  - Robin Winks, "The Joy of the Chase or Sleuthing with Clio", 1979 November 4 (Box 3, Cassette 12)
  - John Taras, "Creativity Problem Solving and the Dance", 1981 April 8 (Box 3, Cassette 13)
  - Robert McKay, "Adversary Justic and the Public Interest", 1978 October 25 (Box 3, Cassette 14)
  - John P. Spiegel, M.D., 1971 December 8 (Box 3, Cassette 15)
  - John R. Platt, 1969 October 8 (Box 3, Cassette 16)
  - Robert B. McKay, "The Future of Affirmative Action E10.2001", 1979 (Box 3, Cassette 17)
  - Robin Winks, "The Mastery of Detection...", 1980 March 19 (Box 3, Cassette 18)
  - John Taras, "Creativity, Problem-Solving, 1981 April 8 (Box 3, Cassette 19)
  - Lawrence Cremin, 1970 April 29 (Box 3, Cassette 20)
  - Robin Winks, "The Art & Science of Professional Snooping", 1978 April 26 (Box 3, Cassette 21)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Deviant Behavior: Beyond Freud & Durkheim, II", 1979 December 5 (Box 3, Cassette 22)
  - Curtis Williams, "The Genesis of an Experiment", 1981 February 25 (Box 3, Cassette 23)
  - Curtis Williams, "The Genesis of an Experiment E10.2002", 1980 April 23 (Box 3, Cassette 24)
  - John P.Spiegel, M.D. "Theory of Variations in Cultural & Subcultural Values-Conflicts & Adaptations", 1976 April 7 (Box 3, Cassette 25)
  - Robert McKay, "Justice and Equality", 1975 October 10 (Box 3, Cassette 26)
  - George Nelson, "Visual Illiteracy", 1976 March 17 (Box 3, Cassette 27)
  - John P. Spiegel, 1969 March 12 (Box 3, Cassette 28)
  - Richard Cloward, "What Did the Poor Get?", 1971 September 29 (Box 3, Cassette 29)
  - Frances Fox Piven, 1970 March 11 (Box 3, Cassette 30)
  - Curtis Macomber, violin; Robert Dan, viola; March Shuman, cello; E10.2001, 1979 October 10 (Box 3, Cassette 31)
  - William J. Sweeney III, M.D. "New Solutions to Gynecological Problems: Microsurgery", 1981 February 11 (Box 3, Cassette 32)
  - Curtis Williams, 1975 October 22 (Box 3, Cassette 33)
  - Frances Fox Piven, Lecture, 1972 March 15 (Box 3, Cassette 34)
  - Anthony Storr, M.D., Lecture, 1971 October 27 (Box 3, Cassette 35)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Theories of Change and Management of Deviant Classes", 1975 December 3 (Box 3, Cassette 38)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Poverty and the Poor", 1972 October 8 (Box 3, Cassette 29)
  - Richard A. Cloward, "Relationship Between Relief Crises and Economic Crises", 1969 October 22 (Box 3, Cassette 40)
  - Robert McKay, "Impeachment-A Lawyer's View", 1974 October 16 (Box 3, Cassette 41)
  - Robert McKay, "Legal Services to the Poor", 1975 December 15 (Box 3, Cassette 42)
  - Gates Lecture, "Ecological Principles and the Environment", 1972 February 9 (Box 3, Cassette 43)
  - Sawhill, "Technology and Economic Growth", 1976 October 20 (Box 3, Cassette 44)
  - Sawhill, "The Future of Democracy", 1975 October 8 (Box 3, Cassette 45)
  - Rosenthal, "Diogenes, Pygmalion & the PONS: Deception, Sex and Eavesdropping in Non-verbal Communication", 1978 October 18 (Box 3, Cassette 46)